What is the role of silence in Buddhism
in the context of speech, internal and
mental silence, and the quiet
environment?
Uh yeah, well, it's um Speech
Speech
is beneficial in as much as it is an
abstinence from
from
unwholesome types of Sorry, silence is
would be wholesome to the extent that
it's an abstinence from unwholesome
types of speech.
But silence in and of itself can be an
action. >> [clears throat]
>> [clears throat]
>> So,
if it's isolated from the context of
avoiding specific unwholesome actions,
then silence could be bad.
That's why the Buddha said uh
to those monks who determined to be
silent for the whole winter retreat,
um
as a blanket observance,
he he compared them He said they were
living like cows.
Living like sheep.
Um
so,
the confusion probably arises because
well, noise is unpleasant.
Noise is sort of uh
it feels nicer when it's quiet.
But that doesn't necessarily mean that
you are absolved of your intentions for
why you're seeking quietude.
So, if you're abstaining from making
noise because making noise is
unwholesome, like for example,
uh idle chatter.
Like, you know, when you're explicitly
like you see your intention, you don't
just uh make this kind of
uh make this kind of
guess as like, "Oh, well, if I speak,
I'm automatically
uh trying to distract myself." Which can
feel that way in the beginning. No, you
actually check,
"Is my mind trying to escape from
something by speaking?" Like, is there some
by speaking?" Like, is there some
internal restlessness that I'm resolving
by speaking?
Which which you will clearly see that if
you decide not to speak,
it's going to feel
uh confining. It's going to feel like
this imprisonment.
Well, that type of speech you don't
engage in. So, in that way, you would be
inclining towards silence as an
abstinence from
uh particular types of speech.
So, um at the same time, you know, like
um at the same time, you know, like
silence has uh Silence has different
implications, or noise has different
implications. Like, there's noise of
Like, there's noise of
uh the possibility of other people
talking to you.
Uh and that can be a disturbance in the
sense that,
you know, as the Buddha said, the
like the the presence of other people
would be a thorn to samadhi.
And that's not because uh you enter some
kind of absorbed state,
but it's just because
even if it's not unwholesome, the
possibility of speaking to other people,
or the the
you feel the the the threat that
somebody could talk to you, well, that
has an effect on your mind. Like, you
don't have the same perspective over yourself
have the same perspective over yourself
when other people are around than when
they're not.
Automatically enter this mode of like uh
seeing yourself in light of other
people. You could say that way.
So, in that sense, it's not the noise
in like that, you know,
neutral noises of
uh birds or or nature, or even
cars or something. It's specifically the
noise of
people potentially talking to you.
potentially talking to you.
People being in the vicinity.
That's what can be a That That's what
can, again, not push you automatically
into unwholesome, but
in the more refined types of
development, when you actually are
trying to cultivate samadhi, that could
become a threat. But the thing is,
uh even then, you would not be justified
in acting out of aversion to the noise
because aversion is one of the five
hindrances. So, if you're acting out of aversion,
So, if you're acting out of aversion,
and you don't see that as a problem, you
can be sure that whatever you will do in
silence is not samadhi.
And that's generally what what people uh
give in to, like the
justified uh
sense of right- righteousness to have a
quiet environment,
uh being being annoyed at disturbances.
Well, you can be sure that then that's
not samadhi. So,
if you're actually heading in that
direction, it's not that you would be disturbed,
it's not that you would be disturbed,
and you would be irritated by the noise.
It would be a just a objective
recognition that, you know,
"Oh, I could go deeper with this if this
wasn't around." But you would know that
for as long as it stays around,
I am only
uh walking backwards
if I get annoyed.
So, uh in that sense, that would be much
closer to, even if the noise never goes
away, um you would be far closer to samadhi by
um you would be far closer to samadhi by
having that attitude of
bearing the discomfort of noise
than by just trying to get rid of it uh
out of that
justified, which which would be
aversion. Like, it's in a It feels
unpleasant. And that unpleasantness pushes you into
And that unpleasantness pushes you into
action.
So, um
So, yeah, those are the two things.
Like, for yourself, you would have to
make sure that
uh noise or conversation on your part
doesn't happen
because of that internal
uh seeking of an escape.
And that's not even measurable
externally. That you only you would know
by asking yourself, like, "How much of a
problem would it be for me not to say
this?" And if you feel like like suddenly that
And if you feel like like suddenly that
makes you a prisoner to your own mind.
Like, it feels like
it's tearing you apart, basically,
because it feels like you really need to
say it.
Uh and even if it feels very important,
actually. Um well, that's that's when you know,
Um well, that's that's when you know,
"Okay, this is based on craving,
clearly." Uh and it's those specific types of
Uh and it's those specific types of
speech that you restrain yourself from.
And uh
that can vary from day to day.
So, like, what what specific uh
conversations or what specific
um topics, like, obviously certain
topics are kind of inherently leading
you in the direction of idle chatter,
which are the topics that the Buddha uh
listed out in many suttas, cuz they
would even if there is a practical purpose for
even if there is a practical purpose for
them,
it's like uh the kind of thing where you
could just go on and on.
And uh it has no connection with the
practice, and it's kind of a
if the mind is seeking external uh
safety and and
um kind of
like I said, that that escape from that
imprisonment, then those are the things that it would
then those are the things that it would
be inclining to naturally.
Uh food, clothing,
gossip, news.
Uh so, it's not that it's inherently
unwholesome >> [snorts]
>> [snorts]
>> uh per se.
It's like
uh Well, first, if it's done for an
escape, which is the really the only time you
which is the really the only time you
would be
putting much effort on you of your own
to
dwell on those topics. Like, it's one
thing when somebody brings it up, and
you sort of
sort of
quickly respond to it not to be
impolite. But then when you know that
you actually want to have a conversation
about this and explore the details of
the topic,
that's explicitly when it becomes idle
chatter. Like, unless there's a
practical reason for it, and it's just
like, "I'm actually interested in this. I want
"I'm actually interested in this. I want
to know more about this."
That's what you should be
put uh keeping an eye out for.
uh keeping an eye out for.
And then anything else, like even if
it's for dhamma purposes, but you see
that it's it's like,
"I really want to talk. Like, I don't
really care what it's about.
It just happens to be that dhamma is
allowable. Therefore, I will speak about
that." It It It would be similar with the
It It It would be similar with the
precepts. When you take that uh
legalistic attitude. Like, "Okay, well,
these specific things are allowed. These
specific things are not allowed." So,
then you you realize, "I want to speak
anyway. I want to talk about something cuz the
I want to talk about something cuz the
pressure is too strong." And then you
realize, "Okay, dhamma is \
\ allowed." Uh then you do it
because because of that same intention,
well, it's not really any different.
If you were speaking about kings and
clothing and everything else. Like, it's
serving the same purpose for you
internally. So,
um
that's the
the the thread that ties it all
together. What are What are your
intentions? So,
So,
could one say that if one practices
silence rightly as an abs- like, silence
is a manifestation of you abstaining
from speaking out of unwholesome
intentions?
Then when you're not silent, when you're
amidst people, or you're talking, it's
more like, you said, when you're
irritated, it's more like you're going
backwards. Actually, that's a sign of
you going in the wrong direction. You're
using silence in the wrong way.
Or it's more like you're trying to get
rid of something through silence.
Whereas when you practice it correctly,
it feels more like, if I understood you
correctly, like putting things on pause,
it's not you're not going forward,
either you're developing through talking
to people, nor are you going back
backward, you're just putting it on
pause. And then when you go back in solitude,
And then when you go back in solitude,
then you don't feel like irritated or
anything, you just feel like you can
pick it up where you left it off in a
way. Mhm. Well, yeah, but it it's
it's not rooted in irritation, your
absence from speaking.
It is rooted in you seeing that for like
right now speaking would give a footing
or a a
it would be catering to
some kind of pressure of the five
hindrances. Uh even if it's just restlessness.
Uh even if it's just restlessness.
So,
for that reason you would be silent. For
that reason you would abstain from
speaking, but if the abstaining from
speaking is the thing that the mind is pressuring
is the thing that the mind is pressuring
you toward,
that's what you realize like well, that
doesn't mean I have to speak.
I should simply
not uh commit myself to this avoidance
of discomfort.
And then you will speak the right
amount. You you don't you won't need to
worry about it because
clearly in that case then,
uh
it wasn't even that your speech was
unwholesome. You were just this or or
your engagement with the situation was
unwholesome. So, then you deal with whatever problem
So, then you deal with whatever problem
or or task you had to deal with.
And naturally you already know that your
mind is tending actually in the opposite
direction of avoiding it.
So, you don't have to worry that you're
doing something unwholesome.
And then now if you went in the opposite
direction of like, oh well, let me seek
out people because I see them and my
mind resisted. Well, easily that would
become where where your mind wants it now.
where where your mind wants it now.
And that's when you would have to stop
it.
There's actually a sutta where the
Buddha says that um essentially
describes purifying the mind.
And then he says,
uh it talks about all the jhanas, and
then it says, um
if a monk then
if his mind inclines towards uh sitting,
any of the four postures, uh he sits or
he stands or he walks. And then it even
says, if his mind inclines towards
speaking, he speaks, or if his mind
inclines towards being silent, he will
be silent. In other words, it's not
automatic as people might think that you would
as people might think that you would
always be silent. It just means that
whether you speak or whether you stay
silent, it's not going to be based on
any of the five hindrances. There's no
like internal impulse
forcing you to do either of those.